this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digitalocean recently launched
spaces a beautifully simple object
storage service designed for developers
who want a simple way to store and serve
a vast amount of data such as images and
large media files user-generated content
backups and logs spaces is available for
a simple $5 per month price that
includes 250 gigabytes of storage and
one terabyte of outbound bandwidth
additional storage is priced at the
lowest rate available one cent per
gigabyte transferred and two cents per
gigabyte stored this provides cost
savings of up to 10 times along with
predictable pricing and no surprises on
your monthly bill try it for free with a
two month trial by going to do SEO / SE
radio welcome to software engineering
radio my name is brian romero gregor
Hopa is chief architect at Allianz where
he is responsible for driving the
digital transformation of one of the
world's largest insurance companies he
is well known as the co-author of the
book enterprise integration patterns and
a contributor to 97 things every
software architect should know and best
software writing gregor is a frequent
speaker at conferences around the world
and as an active member of the I Triple
E software editorial advisory board
Gregor was an early guest of software
engineering radio speaking with us in
episode 42 Gregor has recently authored
a new book titled 37 things one
architect knows about IT transformation
a chief architects journey which we'll
be discussing today
hello Gregor and welcome back to
software engineering radio hi Brian I'm
super happy to be on SEO radio again
thank you so much well to kick off I'd
like to ask a deceptively simple
question or easy - for me to articulate
question what is the role of IT
architecture that is actually a very
good question and not an easy one to
answer they are about as many answers as
they are to
the question you know what is IT right
what is architecture and what does an
architect do in the end
in fact the guy Tripoli maintains a
whole website of definitions of software
architecture leave alone IT architecture
but I often try to describe is that if
you have a system well a couple years
down the road is still functioning well
and is still able to absorb new
requirements that's a sign you probably
had a good architecture nice and what is
the distinction that we can make between
software architecture and enterprise
architecture mm-hmm
so what's a software architecture is one
element of enterprise architecture
almost all software lives in in a
context right it really lives in
isolation especially large enterprise it
will be an interval be interacting with
other systems it will interact with
reporting functions it will be subject
to things like legal regulations or
product launch plans so in the end the
architecture of a software system is one
element and the IT or Enterprise
Architect looks at bringing some harmony
and alignment to all the pieces that
around it this could be the
infrastructure that it's running on this
could be even organizational
considerations right I said or it could
be legal legal and commercial
considerations so bringing all that
together that is really the role of the
IT architect or the Enterprise Architect
so interesting so it sounds like when
you are performing the role of a
Enterprise Architect you're going to
have to be involved with teams that
beyond what we might normally associate
with architecture in strict terms you're
going to be interacting with teams that
are in engineering operations teams
monitoring teams but also legal business
teams sales teams so would you say that
the role of an Enterprise Architect is
is a more collaborative role in its
nature it's definitely facilitating in a
collaborative role in the end of course
it is the architects job to make a
decision or a recommendation on the
overall system architecture and of
course in order to do
so you need to be in touch with the
various stakeholders and group and get
as much input as you can so you find a
good balance between all the different
factors that that come to play and most
importantly avoid two additional
pitfalls where a beautiful software
architecture was developed for a
stateless highly scalable cloud native
system and in the end some legal or data
privacy consideration was neglected and
the system can never go live so in the
end drawing you know that kind of bridge
between the different constituents that
is a key role of the architect and he
absolutely right this involves engaging
with different kind of teams sometimes
in a in a consulting role but more than
a facilitating role to arrive at a joint
decision interesting yeah
so within the organization the role of
the architect where where's that person
within an organization to whom does the
the architect report and and who may
report to the the Enterprise Architect
oh very good questions so different
companies have a different set up for
the enterprise architect or sometimes
the chief architect which is my title so
I in fact actually report to our
divisional CEO so I don't report purely
into the IT and I believe that is
reflection that that architecture at
this scale is not a pure IT topic for
example many of the recent advances we
have in architecture let it be cloud
computing let it be def of style
development big data analytics like knee
all the kind of cool stuff we have
recently working on all these have
significant organizational implications
so let's say you have a fully automated
tool chain and you're basically sitting
in DevOps heaven if you need 25
approvals you know over a quarter to get
some software production all that
brand-new technology doesn't help you at
all so in the end my reporting line
reflects that where the big
technological advantage advances that
we're dealing with these days half
organizer toriel aspects and that's why
I'm actually
to the CEO it will vary though in
different companies where typically the
architect is an IT function and the
chief architect might for example report
to the CIO the chief information officer
then the interesting question becomes
where does the chief information officer
report to because this can tell you a
lot about what is the view of the role
that IT plays on the enterprise but I
think we come back to that later when we
talk about the topic of IT
transformation well actually I think
that's a great segue I'd like to discuss
that because at that level given the
nature of the role of an Enterprise
Architect with all the teams and with
with whom you must interact and and
their structure within the organization
it sounds like the architect plays a big
role into the organization itself not
just the not just the architecture of
infrastructure and software or services
together so your book is titled 37
things one architect knows about IT
transformation so may I ask what is IT
transformation mmm-hmm
very well and from the little bit
tongue-in-cheek title you can tell that
the book is really very much about what
I've been doing in the last couple of
years and this is driving IT
transformation from the perspective of
an architect so it's really 37 episodes
out of my my daily life if you wish well
why are we dealing with IT
transformation it's quite simple if you
look at the technology landscape out
there it's quite obvious that that
allows five to ten years things have
changed dramatically and not just in the
smartphone we hold in our hands but also
in the demands on enterprise IT digital
companies tend to operate quite
differently to a traditional IT shop in
the past when IT shop it was MIA it was
acceptable that it takes weeks a month
or sometimes a year to provision a
single server software updates were
really done right we know the old slogan
never touched a running system once
things were running you know you leave
them alone as long as you can the
digital world works very differently the
digital works worse off
world works of what I call economies of
speed they release software quickly they
get feedback cycles they modify and
refine all the time now businesses that
can operate in that fashion
put pressure on traditional businesses
now that pressure relates also to the
demands on those traditional businesses
IT the business will ask well why does
it take us so long or why is it so
expensive to deploy a new piece of
software why can go --gel Facebook
Amazon Microsoft do X and we cannot so
in the end the IT has to respond to
those demands and that's what drives IT
transformation and when do you recognize
that a transformation is necessary in in
some cases it sounds like what you're
describing is a desire to achieve a
degree of flexibility and a degree of
responsiveness to the business concerns
at what point do you does an architect
may be responsible for triggering an IT
transformation or recognizing when
that's necessary within an organization
so I teach a lot of workshops and we
actually played with this thought is
like are there enterprises that don't
have to worry about digital disruption
or digital transformation at all like
all the business where you say I keep
doing the same thing I've always been
doing and I'll be fine in five 10 15 20
years in the end we had a hard time
coming up with any the sort of most
funny ironic one that somebody mentioned
was a funeral home you know and says oh
they don't have to worry about digital
disruption I teach transformation but in
the end we even debunked that idea
because if you think about it today
folks have a notion of a digital legacy
right like your parents have photos
online on Facebook or Flickr people pass
away who takes over their accounts and
who can maintain the digital legacy so
even the sort of seemingly endlessly far
hit top hit off of funeral homes right
and dealing with sort of very different
aspects of life right those are even
subject to digital disruption and
or to diesel digital transformation so
if as an architect you have a feeling
that digital transformation doesn't
impact you I'll really challenge you to
think about whether this is true and if
you sure you are let me know because I'm
really looking for an example so it
sounds like that this is one of the
cases the benefit of having an architect
devoted to this perspective is is very
important is to think of these aspects
or these cases where the handling future
future changes as you say with the the
funeral home like who handles that
material who handles that necessary
those digital assets might not be
something that other teams in the
organization and engineering team is is
focusing on intently so they might right
because the the project teams that build
individual software they will have some
idea that there's there's new demands
that there's a need as you say for more
responsiveness more speed in from from
the business side however they are often
in a traditional IT shop they're stuck
in a certain context right they depend
on the infrastructure right so if they
can't get a server right they won't be
fast they won't be responsive now they
can think about moving into the cloud
their legal might come and say oh this
is personal information maybe we do
wouldn't like to have this in the cloud
or if it's in the cloud it must be
inside the you are inside North America
right and that's where you see that that
these kind of transitions often touch on
a much broader scope than an individual
application or project team and this is
where the role of the ite or the enter
by scale IT architecture becomes so
critical in getting this transformation
underway mm-hmm you know it sounds like
that kind of a transformation can be
done driven by business requirements or
business forces how is it what would you
define the boundaries between business
concerns and an IT and how does a
an enterprise architect traverse those
two areas of business and IT I often say
that the business doesn't care about
architecture and I say this as the chief
architect and the interesting answer to
that or correlate to that is and they
shouldn't right what do you do with the
architecture what the system is designed
like in the end that is really I tease
all the architects business what the
business does care a lot about though is
how the system behaves you can it absorb
a sustained rate of change does it scale
is it secure so on the end what
behaviors are characteristics your
architecture leads to is immensely
relevant to the business and
understanding the business priorities is
one of the key factors for the
architecture what keeps architecture so
interesting and the job of the architect
so interesting is that it's all about
balances and trade-offs you can't have
everything at once right a a more
maintainable system might be slightly
more complex and more highly performing
system might be more difficult to
understand more secure system might have
a larger footprint it's all about
trade-offs and balances and in the end
the IT has one purpose I t's purpose is
to deliver value to the business getting
the business in the end brings the money
and allows the company to exist so the
architect needs to really understand
what the business's priorities are now
the business doesn't come in and say
here are 20 architectural needs that we
have when we thought them all through
and they're sorted one through twenty
right in the end this is part of the
discovery process so I would expect an
architect to have a fairly good
understanding of the business side like
what are the market forces if you work
an international company where's the
money being made where are the cash cows
where are the growing markets where are
the opportunities that is also part of
the job of an architect so in that
process of discovery where the architect
is interfacing with the business they
are understanding where the priorities
are what the market forces are what is
the cadence by which the the architect
should be doing that
how often and how regularly should the
architect be speaking and syncing with
the business there yeah this is probably
one of the most difficult aspects of
being an architect in this role because
in the end many different lines of
communication run together and the value
of the architect really lies in to
bringing those together and balancing
them at bringing this into a cohesive
solution now the biggest danger is since
you're dealing with so many aspects that
you lose focus that you get distracted
right because you could spend all your
day on the business side you can spend
all your day in the infrastructure you
could spend all your day with the
application teams you can also spend all
day with the vendors telling you about
new great technology they have developed
so on the end I've never found a recipe
for how to balance that except to do it
in a in a very self-aware calibration
cycle driven by a clear goal and the
clear goal has to be business value of
that is being delivered and and that has
to be the function you optimize and
calibrate by and then it's a daily
struggle if you wish or a daily
balancing act to find the the right
cadence to to interact with the
different teams this is really what
makes the job interesting but also
challenging yeah I bet and fascinating
as well
the is it also a responsibility of the
architect to articulate that value that
you're trying to achieve to teams like
engineering and operations and
development the architect needs to
provide that visibility or that vision
down to those parts of the organization
I think it certainly helps how much an
architect has to do that depends a
little bit on the project set up if your
IT in the software delivery is very
close to the business like they interact
very closely with a product owner for
example then they generally have a very
good feeling for the value that their
system provides if that is not given
then I would say it's appropriate for an
architect to inject a little bit more I
find when I look at software projects
it's often a me
how much effort is made to build things
that I in the end not needed or provide
very little value there's a famous quote
near optimizing things that are not
needed at all is one of the silliest
things to do unfortunately suffer
delivery projects are often burned very
much with doing that to the extent that
an architect can help inject a little
bit there it might be helpful but I
would be cautious to not interfere if
there's a very healthy relationship with
the business already interesting so how
is it that an architect can lead
transformation I imagine that a
transformation can be there's risks
associated with transformation IT
transformation but it's determined that
it's necessary
what is the architects role in leading
that transformation sure transformation
it's all about change right is about
actually dramatic change when we say
transformation and of course change
bears risk I almost remind folks though
that no change also bears risk now
that's the lesson learned from the Codex
and the blockbusters of the world right
who did not respond to digital
disruption and hence the the risk of of
no change can be the risk of losing the
business so in the end right it's it's
about realizing that the change is
inevitable now the architects role in
that I would say is lives on multiple
dimensions there's the technology aspect
right in the end the IT needs to be able
to deliver the basic services that the
business needs to compete in a digital
world I mentioned earlier I call this
the economies of speed it's about taking
out friction out of the system all right
and this can be if you if you go down
into the into the detail what I call the
architect elevator right if you take
this down into the engine room you're
delivering software faster and getting
rid of friction involves things like
methods involves methods you know like
like DevOps approaches and lean
approaches but it also involves classic
technology this can be automation you
know this is the answer Bowl chef puppet
salt kind of a domain this
can be docker containers and packaging
so it goes down very much deep in the
technology with a clear view of what
value it brings to the business and that
is speed of deployment not forgetting
organizational aspect right because if
you have a fully automated continuous
delivery pipeline but you need to run
around twelve departments to get
approvals and this will take you three
months you still haven't made the
organization faster so on the end it's
the combination between delivering the
hard tools the technological basis for
for faster soft delivery plus the
organizational enablement to it I think
that combination is what makes the
architect so important in an IT
transformation scenario yeah we had
discussed in we had a episode 287 with
Neil Ford discussing success skills for
architects and your your that during
that conversation that episode your your
analogy of the elevator the elevator
metaphor was also mentioned can you
we're talking about the elevator of
course being that that there's different
layers in an organization and the
architect rides that elevator up and
down and and must be able to communicate
with different people at those elevators
sometimes being able to go very low
level into engineering disciplines but
also communicating how the architecture
meets the the value the business value
provides a business value to high-level
executives soft skills sound like a very
important aspect of the leadership
that's required in an IT transformation
and I would imagine that's you would
feel that a major factor of the
capability to communicate as a major
factor so the architect elevator is
really the key metaphor of my book and
the end I was actually thinking whether
I should call it the architect elevator
and I opted for a little bit near the
longer tongue-in-cheek title we are
dusty elevator metaphor originated large
organizations are hierarchical right and
often this is an aspect we don't like
some
because you need to go to the boss the
boss's boss the buzzers buzz to get a
decision but in the end hierarchies work
well otherwise these companies wouldn't
be so successful they work well though
in a relatively static world it's just
like hierarchies like layering me one of
the most widely used architectural
patterns I would say riot is layering we
know very well a hierarchy is a layered
organization and it has all the same
benefits that layering does in IT
architecture it hides abstraction its
division of labor division of concerns
clean interfaces you can take one layout
and replace it with another layer
sometimes we call this IT outsourcing
right so there's many good reasons why
they layered layer architectures have
disadvantages as well though for
something Duke travel end-to-end for a
whether this is a request in a technical
system that has to go from the user
interface all the way to the database or
whether it's at each strategic decision
in an organization that has to be
translated into an IT implementation it
has to diverse many many different
layers and that's like a skyscraper
there's just a lot of floors in this
organization so and sometimes there's a
hundred floors and up in the penthouse
where you have the company leadership
sits when they define a strategy when
they see something on the horizon and
say we should be doing X and the
traditional organization that topic X
goes to the next floor down and the next
floor and the next floor it goes to the
upper management the upper middle
management the middle management near
the lower management and by the time it
arrives in the engine room where actual
software is being delivered you have two
major problems one it takes a long time
and we already learned that in the
digital world right in the economies of
speed being slow is is not a very good
thing and B it has the effect of the
telephone game right we're the story
that started once in the top floors by
the time it arrives or the basement is
probably a quiet different story hence
the analogy of the elevator we need to
stop passing things down floor by floor
it's nice and convenient because you
only have to worry about what's going on
on your
but because of these dramatic downsides
the model is no longer appropriate in a
digital world so we need somebody to
move faster between the different levels
and I feel the architects are the folks
who are best equipped because generally
they have a good technical background
but they also have the communication and
social skills to interact at the upper
floors of the penthouse so that has
really become the the guiding metaphor
for the role of an architect in IT
transformation I'd like to ask more
about some more questions with regard to
how an architect both must adjust to the
organization they find themselves in and
also influence the organization to what
degree does the architect have
responsibility for setting the
organizational architecture it occurs to
me in many cases that the IT
architecture may be dictated by the
organization itself the enclosing
organization what is the responsibility
of the IT architect influence the
organization itself so I sometimes joke
that I'm actually the organizational
engineer disguised as the chief
architect in the end the two topics are
inseparable and they are the most famous
or the incarnation of that is the
well-known Conway's law that in the end
you know the architecture of a system
resembles the organizational structure
and if you look to some extent you know
what we have seen with micro services we
often call that the reverse Conway which
means you choose a system architecture
that allows you to to have a matching
organizational structure the one of
smaller teams and independent releases
so the two are very closely linked and
that's why in the architect these days
has to concern himself or herself with
organizational aspects I often say that
all the problems we had that we can
solve with technology alone we cannot
pretty much solved right if you look at
let's say like some of the open source
project over many many folks are
speaking at conferences etc it used to
be very developer focus we worked on
ideas and other open source like eclipse
and a lot of tooling and continuous
integration came about
and now if you see that where people put
their thoughts and and their energy it's
a very much about run time right so
people talk much more how do I get stuff
in production or how do I run the
software this is all the cloud docker or
grant um infrastructure and with that
they get closer to what organizational
structure do I need because now the view
that we have is much more of an
end-to-end view right when you look at
an ID it's more like okay how do i code
this piece of software but when you
start talking about continuous
integration continuous delivery cloud
runtimes
now you're thinking about how can I get
this software more quickly into the
hands of a customer and with this
broadening of the scope organizational
aspects suddenly step into the
foreground and this is the example I
gave before I the full automated CD
pipeline doesn't help you anything if
you need 15 approvals between different
apparent departments to get budget to
get authorization to get a legal
sign-off to get security sign-off etc so
you're not going to be spared from the
organizational topics yeah and we had
covered aspects of infrastructure as
code in episode 268 with Keith Morris
but discussing this more about IT
architecture or infrastructure should
operations teams as a result as the
advent of infrastructure as code coming
into the industry should operations
teams now be adopting the practices and
methodologies of used in software
development now there's this this change
occurring so operations teams face a lot
of pressure these days right on one hand
they see all this transformation going
on particularly on the cloud computing
side a lot of internal IT transformation
are seeing the infrastructure that they
manage move off into the cloud and often
worried actually about their existence
so it's it's not an easy job to be in
because for one you need to deal with
production incidents but be people also
see the writing on the wall and say well
will this at some point all run
near Amazon Google Microsoft's cloud my
view on this is that operations is
actually more important than ever if you
look at the operational demands of
modern systems is actually quite amazing
I mean everybody wants 24/7 unlimited
scalability updates without any down
times etc etc so these are all
operational concerns so on the end
operations is as relevant and more
relevant than ever but this one caveat
what operations looks like has changed
and that is very much to what you
mentioned through the software-defined
infrastructure traditional manual
operations has two stands no chance to
keep up with the demands of the business
and the demands of the application
development teams you can't have
continuous deployment red green deploys
you know many times a day without any
down times if there are any manual
processes involved aybe out of
consideration for speed and B out of
consideration of quality I have one
chapter my book I call it never send the
human to do a machines job one of the
matrix quotes but it's a hundred percent
true in operations as soon as you have
humans involved the error rate goes up
tenfold or hundredfold humans are great
at creative tasks at creating new things
ideas humans are inherently bad at
performing repetitive tasks and nowhere
is this more obvious than in the
software development of software
delivery to me this is actually one of
the sort of ironies of software delivery
right how did how did IT get big in
their business right why do we have
large IT departments because we
automated the business around the
business you have work for an insurance
company what did the business used to do
they used to write everything on paper
and then shuffle people from left s to
right desk they do huge calculations for
risk models by hand on paper and we have
automated this all that's why we exist
because we've we've gained enormous
efficiencies for the business but if you
look at the way software used to be
delivered right it was sort of manual
craft work somebody coffees files
Pachi um they're a little configuration
over here right it was basically we were
manufacturing software the way the
business manufactured 50 years ago now
with DevOps and your suffer define
infrastructure and infrastructure as a
code that has rapidly changed and it's
leading to a full automation of many of
the infrastructure concerns so that's
fantastic right it takes a lot of the
friction out as always there's one catch
and it comes back to our topic of of
organizational management software
defined infrastructure or infrastructure
as a code is much more than scripting
alright you can write a little script a
little shell script you know a little
ansible whatever have you ride to
automate some of your tasks and at the
surface you might think oh look now my
infrastructure is software-defined
because remember a piece of software
does that that that does what I did by
hand before that is a very small step
though and you're really missing the the
major point to to transition from a
little scripting a little bit automation
to really software-defined
infrastructure it's all about adopting
software best practices in this context
and that means things like version
control things like testing things like
collaboration things like continuous
deployment that's where your transition
into really software-defined
infrastructure and and those as a
mindset that is a mindset that is much
closer to a software development mindset
and you can apply this to your
infrastructure and ultimately you will
find that by using the same mindset
along the whole software delivery
lifecycle from coding the features to
deploying the stuff into production you
take an enormous amount of friction out
of the system and that is exactly what
allows you to compete with the digital
giants so it'll it's the going to be the
case that we would predict that
operations teams are going to adopt more
and more of the best practices of
software development that have come from
that area so it definitely sounds like
operation seems will be adopting the
methodologies developed in with regard
to software development or
are these teams going to become more
tightly coupled in the operation team is
going to be have to become more tightly
coupled in support of the software teams
that they're supporting or managing yes
and no I think they'll have to think
much more alike and also interact more
on the other hand I think a solid
division of responsibilities clean
interfaces are a key aspect of it you
take cloud computing as an example
you're the big cloud providers now the
Amazon Google Microsoft of the world
right they do operations but you never
interact with any of the people that do
operations there right it's fantastic
it's all done through self-service ap is
on the end it's interesting right people
talk about DevOps right and DevOps sort
of meaning bringing death or Nobbs
closer together and I would say from the
tooling and mindset perspective that is
really the essence of DevOps right
taking the friction out of the system
and being able to get softened from
production quickly that's my my favorite
definition of DevOps it's actually from
Landis s book right DevOps for
architects however that doesn't mean
they need to be part of one team or you
know sit together and have a beer
together all the time right this can
mean that they have the same overall
goal in the overall mindset but still
fairly distinct responsibilities give
you an example from my daily life if we
built a private cloud runtime platform
well that's part of what we did as the
architecture team and obviously we live
very much at the at the intersection
between development and end operations
and infrastructure at the same time
responsibilities are very clearly
separated if the platform doesn't run
our problem if the platform runs but the
application doesn't your problem now
a division of responsibilities doesn't
have to be a blame game like it used to
be right the operation says hey servers
up you know what do you want then
application says oh I don't have any
bugs what do you want and I think that
taking that finger pointing that blaming
that aspect out that was makes the
essence between getting operations
development teams more closely to make
sure they have aligned as the fall as
opposed to conflicting goals if you
think about classic operations versus
development what is developments job to
get as many changes into production as
possible well what was operations job
well to keep stable operations and one
way to do that is to get as few changes
into production as possible never touch
a running system now the death of
approach gives them the same mindset and
that is with a high degree of automation
and a software mindset you know unit
testing version control tight team
collaboration etc you can you know have
your cake and eat it too you can you go
eat your cake and have it too right you
can push changes into production rapidly
and frequently without jeopardizing
operational stability and that's really
the essence of of DevOps it's not about
making one team out of it but to have
them both play their respective role of
a new way of developing and delivering
software so it may be the case that like
agile you had mentioned earlier that
agile had been misunderstood that
documentation people say I don't
document because I'm an agile this
aspect of development and operations or
DevOps may have been misunderstood is
that you can have these divisions of
responsibility which are divisions of
concern which can be beneficial for
these teams to concentrate on but the
the real factor the beneficial factor is
to have the communication channels open
and understanding open that the teams
understand what it is that they need to
be working on what it is that they're
supporting mutually and these new
practices of related from
infrastructures code facilitate this
kind of cross collaboration cross
communication yeah this is one of my pet
peeves in big IT once a buzzword you
know gets real traction people start
abusing it for everything as that people
say well we'll make silly calls like oh
I don't have documentation because I'm
agile right I'm
I can do XYZ because I'm DevOps and
people just likes it the Deaf on the UPS
team's next to each other and say look
now I have deaf ups here Steffen ops
right so this is unfortunate right
people always look for the snake oil for
the for the magic bullet and and keep
doing that so this is one of the things
I think architects are well-equipped to
debunk ed we have the technical depth to
say like Hana DevOps is more than
sitting deaf and ops next to each other
to your specific question I think it's
about yeah it's about communication and
mutual understanding but that's just one
aspect in the end the DevOps approach
make sure that operations becomes an a
enabler rather than a disabler and I
gave a classic example that I use in my
workshops let's say your online retailer
when is the most valuable time to push a
code change and sometimes people don't
say oh Sunday morning 2:00 a.m. and said
no that's the safest time it's not the
most valuable time the most valuable
time is right in the Christmas business
when you're running the highest traffic
because the code change you'll be
pushing will either fix a problem that
you're having or release a valuable
feature to your customers and the most
valuable time to launch that is when you
have the most traffic then you have the
most value now yeah I work for a large
insurance company I can tell you exactly
what do we have around their time frozen
zone you're not allowed to put anything
in production because we afraid
something might break and this is where
in the old model developmental
operations as I mentioned have
conflicting goals and this will be seen
by one team as the other team being
disabling rather than enabling oh we
have a new release of software ready we
would like to deploy this if operations
only let us and operations likewise what
these guys always push in your code as
soon as we have the thing half stable
they push something new and break it
again if they could only stop doing that
and the DevOps approach is about
operations becoming an enabler for the
business you want to pay off for the
development teams right so you want to
push software every minute fine you can
do that because I have continuous
delivery I have on my automatic
deployment
have a pass like a platform as a
software as a service infrastructure
that allows you to deploy so fast often
as you like and you know what it doesn't
harm my infrastructure and it doesn't
harm my platform so on the end you've
created an interface you created
self-service you become an it enabler
for the software delivery teams and now
they will thank the operation teams
rather than being a blocker in some
world I never let us deploy software now
we're saying isn't this fantastic the
operation teams built an infrastructure
for us that allows us in a self-service
fashion to deploy software whenever we
feel like it and as it might happen if
we deployed something that doesn't work
or has issues we have the level of
automation version control that we can
revert very very very quickly and can
get back into a stable State and minutes
or seconds often without the customer
even knows that noticing and I think
that is really the big change and and
people like to latch on to these
buzzwords rightly as I said this era
where DevOps Stephanopolous sitting here
because obviously sitting them together
is a very easy thing to do really
transforming right and really changing
the way the teams interact is much much
harder so of course people like to claim
the easy route like to take the easy
route and claim the easy success but of
course unfortunately that is completely
meaningless right it's it's things like
agile I clean like DevOps even things
like near cloud computing they're
fundamentally transformative you can't
do lip service to them you know that
comes back to the essence what an
architecture does today has a lot to do
with IT transformation now a great
aspect of IT transformation often we
might orient ourselves to thinking about
then what the system shall be or what
the next the next iteration of the
development cycle and the features that
bring or transforming to a new
architecture but there's a need to
discuss the end of a system at the end
of a lifespan of a system the life cycle
which you wish to retire systems
organizations often orient when we think
about transformations they're orienting
themselves towards migrating to new
systems new ways of handling things and
some of the resistance that we get back
as you've noted is never touch a working
system but there are times in software
lifespans life cycles that systems do
need to be retired as part of the
transformation when do you identify that
a system should be retired you know
system retirement is a it's an
interesting topic right people usually
don't like to talk about it as much I
often say it's like talking about a
prenup yeah do you just fall in love and
you're planning your honeymoon right you
don't want to talk about a prenup what
happens you know should we part and the
same is true for Sofia you're building a
new system you're buying something from
the vendor everybody is very excited the
last thing you do want to talk about is
what actually happens when the system
retires that would be a major or fault
though have a major flaw because in the
end we serve near the digiworld list of
economies of speed things move faster
that means also things aged faster right
so you need to think much more about the
end of life so for example we guide our
architecture by by a set of IT
characteristics when we build a system
or looking to buy something what are
some of the characteristics that are
important to us and one of them is for
example data extraction being able to
get the data back out of the system so
we can migrate it to the to the
subsequent systems we spoke earlier
about enterprise architects I think
landscape management is really a key
aspect of often Enterprise Architect
often we say the job of an Enterprise
Architect is more like that of a
gardener right it's not the person who
makes all the decisions but it's the
person who sort of trims and prions a
little bit here and there because stuff
grows by itself all the time especially
the weeds you know they grow the fastest
and that is true in the garden as well
as in the IT so often the architect's
job is not actually so much to create
more new things but actually to prune to
trim to retain a balance and it's just
like in the garden if you never do that
you know suddenly
think we'll outgrow each other and
you'll have a giant a giant mess and the
same happens in IT so managing the
lifecycle I would say it's actually one
on getting rid of stuff if you want to
call it bluntly is one of the the key
tasks I have a you know if you're
looking for catchy slogan related to
this I often say write if you never kill
anything you live among zombies and you
know the zombies will eat your brain and
while it sounds yeah a little bit funny
it's actually very true in IT if you
don't if you're not able to to shut off
systems to do end-of-life you will spend
a majority of IT budget and to IT brain
on maintaining old systems it does eat
your brain and it will have no ability
to deliver new features and in the
digital world that's death that doesn't
work yeah that's actually one of my
favorite metaphors from the from the
book is kill get rid of zombies
otherwise they will eat your brain
how can an architect avoid having that
kind of situation occur that a product
lingers and any oal phase indefinitely
but what active steps must be done - or
defined to achieve a complete
end-of-life phase and as with many of
the topics that we're discussing today
again there's an organizational aspect
and there's a technical aspect to it and
we're living at that intersection as an
architect the organizational aspects are
really the business needs to have a
willingness to let some things go right
off we can't retire system because there
is one customer left on the system or we
sell life insurance right life insurance
hopefully runs a long time you're good
for the customer so these customers on
the system now if you want to retire
that system it should be allowed to ask
obvious questions like can we just pay
out that one customer or that set of
customers or can we ask him to migrate
to another product they may not want to
but maybe we can make a deal maybe we
can offer them something the business
will say oh you know that's very
difficult well how difficult is it
really how expensive is it all right
these are all aspects that play directly
into the ability
to retire in a system right so it must
be discussion between business and IT on
the IT side the best way I have to think
about retirement is retirement it's just
one element of the change cycle and you
shouldn't think of it as anything
unusual once a company an organization
embraces the notion that a system is
undergoing constant change retiring your
systems suddenly will see much less
scary because you're used to the fact
that you can automate that you could
bring new features that you can bring
change you that you connect your system
to new features right so suddenly the
idea of taking out some features and
slowly winding a system down is also
changed just with a different sign on
the Delta instead of adding stuff you're
removing stuff and once you're used to
the fact that you have fully automated
testing you have automated deployment
you some leave you become much more
comfortable with this up to the point
where we trying a system is nothing and
unusual so in the old days releasing a
new piece of software was something very
unusual right people would do it on the
weekend stay up all night and you'll
cross their fingers light a candle
whatever they do they just make sure
their software upgrade or this new
release would go well for now we do it
on an hourly basis and we often don't
even notice when it happens
I think the same has to happen with
retiring systems they used to be like
the worst thing that can happen in IT it
just must become normal change is normal
and retiring a system shutting down a
system is just one incarnation of change
so is it the case that there there may
be a requirement for an organization to
become to have an IT transformation a
major IT transformation but is it the
case that some organizations should
should be thinking in terms of
continuous transformation yes in the end
and I would say that is really the the
levels of organizational change you can
be at if you think about a lot of IT
separates change from run right change
or the software project where you know
changes down new features are being
delivered and
run is separate meaning run is no change
alright and we talked about this before
that this is the eternal conflict but
but it has a meaning at the higher level
it means that in such an organization
change is the unusual state all right
like run is the normal state we're happy
when stuff runs and when change has to
happen we get a little bit nervous it's
the the extraordinary state that's why
there are so many gating and control
functions right you need to get budgets
and budget approvals and reviews and
deployment reviews right like we're all
dealing with the fact that change is a
little bit uncomfortable that change is
sort of the unusual thing in the digital
world right if you really want to want
to want to get there you have to abandon
the notion that change is something
unusual and even the word transformation
kind of tends to make you think that
this is all this is something we do sort
of once we kind of transform and once we
transform we are in a better world now I
wish then was so because our job would
be much easier but if you look at the
rate of change and the way the world
especially the digital world evolves
there's no sign that change will slow
down so you need to get used to no
longer thinking of change as something
unusual that has to be contained and
checked and controlled into something
that is just the normal state you will
have continuous change and with that to
some extent you will also have
continuous transformation yeah I guess
the that's an interesting aspect is that
taking an examination of what is the
true nature of how an organization
performs and delivers code and and
maintains code and delivers value is not
so much that you're seeking a steady
state of running operation but you
identify embrace and enhance the change
process identifying the change process
is actually a key characteristic of the
of the industry am i correct in that
assessment yeah I would say these days
it's all about the rate of change you
can maintain there's the famous Jack
Welch quote if
the rate of change outside the
organization is higher than on the
inside the end is near right so building
for stability and considering change to
be the abnormal case works well in a
static case because dealing with change
is tricky it's difficult right it's like
if you don't have to change that's
always easier but if the world around
you is changing then it's all about what
rate of change you can maintain in an
organization so with that in mind I
often say that architects really live
from the first derivative if you have a
system or even an organization that
doesn't need to change at all you
probably have much less need for
architecture and therefore for
architects right you get it running
somehow once and you never touch it
again so the rate of change drives
architectural needs some simple examples
scaling is effective it's a form of
change right scaling is a change in load
that the system needs to handle and a
change in the size of the infrastructure
that then it goes through that requires
architecture we want horizontal scaling
stateless services etc so I really feel
that the rate of change is what drives
the need for the architect now we live
in times of rapid change so that is good
for architects because we're very much
needed and I jobs are very exciting
because of that I would say also that we
also covered a topic in episode 236 with
a Rebecca Parsons on evolutionary
architectures as well but in this case
of course the special circumstance that
architects find themselves of course is
is part of that organizational change
and just as a kind of final thought here
of course your your book is full of
really helpful metaphors and stories and
examples even I found that that you're
saying that an architect lives in it's
that first derivative really interesting
would you say that it's mastery of
metaphor is an important characteristic
of a successful architect and the idea
of interfacing with the organization and
providing change to the organization
yeah I I wouldn't go quite as far
because I think that's a little bit
me myself my style I like making these
metaphors so yeah it's a book about I
teach transformation yes at the end
that's full of zombies and pac-man's and
and matrix quotes right so I think this
is a little bit how how my brain works
but I think there are some serious
aspects to it if you think about what
makes an architect and an architect what
can an architect duel that maybe other
people don't do right you'll quickly
find that it's it's thinking in
abstractions thinking in patterns
thinking in systems right and you know
this is something that makes an
architect a successful architect and and
this the abstraction there's defining
models that has a little bit to do with
metaphors right it's the ability to
connect different seemingly unconnected
things like organizational legal aspects
with technical aspects so in the end
while you know my metaphors always a
little bit tongue-in-cheek and maybe
express more my personality I think that
if you think like an architect you find
that that making these these metaphors
will will help you in your in your
thinking and it's a natural byproduct if
you wish it has one more advantage in
that often the metaphors can make things
less threatening right it can put a
little bit of of human this because in
the end you have to be clear we don't do
transformations in areas for fun right I
mean it's because there's pressure on
the business and some businesses will
not survive you're the digital
transformation right there's a whole
graveyard right off of you know
bookstores and other traditional
businesses that don't exist anymore so
this is serious business right this is
serious talk also between the
departments all right some departments
like operations department made a field
I you know they're not needed anymore I
already said I don't believe in that but
a lot of people do feel this so having
some light-hearted metaphors like often
I call you know documenting in
architecture like sketching tank robbers
ride you ask what did the person look
like and you draw a picture and refined
I find that these metaphors take a
little bit the fear out of the whole
thing and I think this is a really
important ingredient into into making
people part of
successful transformation well thank you
so much for your time and joining us
today
any last aspects or things that you wish
that our listeners to understand about
IT transformation that we have not
covered yeah I would say in the end what
I'd like to give our listeners is that
with the advent of the digital world and
the associated transformation the role
of the architect has really changed a
lot
we used to focus much more on software
architecture but now as we discuss we're
realizing that there's many many more
factors at play particularly
organizational aspects now what I like
to give our listeners like many of mine
them might think I'm an IT guy I'm a
technology guy why do I need to deal
with these organizational aspects and
I'm not maybe very good at it it's like
politics is dealing with people well you
know it's it's not what what I think my
profession is what you'll find there is
that the way organizational systems
behave is not that dissimilar to the way
technical systems behave I give a simple
example right when we build scalable
systems we know that one of the worst
things you can do is put a
synchronization point because the a
synchronization means something happens
at the same time if two things have to
happen at the same time one has to wait
for the other is inevitable like a high
throughput system waiting is probably
not what you want your system to do what
is the organization and analogy we know
we all know it extremely well it's
called the meeting now and when does the
meeting happen maybe next weeks maybe in
two weeks maybe after persons vacation
it's a organizational synchronization
point and just like this kills the
stupid and your technical system it also
kills the Stroop in an organization if
you if you need to make an important
decision and the organizational culture
is such that a meeting is needed yeah
and the meeting involves some important
people who are not available and the
meeting happens in three weeks you just
lost three weeks and your throughput is
horrible so in the end while the role of
the architect has broadened a lot I
convinced that you know the way we think
the way our brain
means work to do good systems
architecture also applies to
organizations so I think it's a great
step for an architect to to move more
into that world because the way your
brain works already equips you very well
to do so and hence I would really like
and to encourage the architects too to
go and do that and to look more broadly
at system architecture it sounds
fantastic
so Gregor a lot of what you're espousing
is change in the digital environment and
and being able having the capacity to
adapt and move quickly is is writing
books a valuable way to get information
out in this day and age that's a that's
a very good question I guess
traditionally books are associated with
taking a long time and by the time the
book comes out you know the information
might already be be aged or relevant
interestingly the digital transformation
hasn't stopped from the way books are
published as well so when I thought
about writing a book about digital
transformation I was wondering would it
actually be appropriate to make this as
a print book which takes a while to come
out just like you described and in the
end I decided to self publish the book
and these days you have have many great
platforms to do so so on the end the way
you write a book becomes much more in
tune with the way the digital world
works you can publish parts of the book
before it's even finished and kept get
feedback cycles right and that that's
what I've done in the end I started
publishing this on on lean pop on this
platform right and basically these days
you can have a book with your readers
before you even done writing and I think
that exactly reflects the spirit of the
digital world so I would say yes writing
books is still very much relevant but
yeah write them in a slightly different
way apply what you learned from the
digital world to the way you write books
yeah a true a true adoption in a spousal
of the agile technologies or agile
methodologies that improve our code
improve any aspect of exchanging
information knowledge and the book is
available online pub
stuff publishes you had mentioned I
would encourage listeners to read it I
enjoyed it a great deal thank you very
much yeah thanks for having me it was a
great pleasure again this has been Brian
or an arrow for software engineering
radio thanks for listening to Nessie
radio an educational program brought to
you by out your police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SCO
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
that will reach us on LinkedIn Facebook
Twitter or through our slack channel at
SC radio slack calm you can also email
us at team at SC dash radio net this and
all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening